but really looking forward to this.
This this feedback loop that we really need to understand if AI
is is truly helping us in our production code or not.
So please welcome on stage Justin Cormack.
Cheers.
Nice to be here.
Great event.
Hi to everyone who's online as well.
I love tests and I've always liked tests.
So with AI, you know, I enjoyed thinking about testing a lot more.
I live in the East of England in the middle of nowhere.
This is our local infrastructure.
This is a Roman road.
This is what happens if you don't maintain your infrastructure.
I love infrastructure, software and it's kind of my thing.
And a while ago, last, like middle of last year, Mineo
stopped maintaining their S3-compatible object storage product
and lots of people complained and said, oh, we like we like this product.
And I'm very obsessive about object storage.
I gave this talk at KubeCon a few years ago.
It's one of the most watched talks from KubeCon about object
storage, and earlier this year, I was kind of looking for a
project to experiment with this.
I wanted to understand what happened if you tried to use AI to right really
large, complex systems because it was great
fun writing small tools with AI, and you could write them really fast
in half a day.
And it was exciting.
But like, could you really build huge things?
Object storage, to give you an idea.
Most of the implementations I've looked at take around
at least two years to write, some of them a decade.
You know, these are big projects.
And so I thought, well, how hard could it be?
I might just give this a go.
Maybe I can do it in a week.
And like, I knew this was going to be a big project.
I was kind of excited about building a big project.
At the moment, it's 350,000 lines of rust, so I was new.
I wasn't going to read the code. I
have only ever half learned rust anyway,
and reading the code is kind of annoying.
It's going to be a huge and complex, and I don't necessarily need to understand it
all, but I know I want high quality code, and that was my thing,
and I knew there was plenty of scope for things to go wrong.
I was building distributed systems, complex stuff, and I was going to reverse
engineer this entire thing by talking to S3 and seeing how it works with my AI.
So it was like this was going to be kind of fun.
I knew I wanted to broadly understand the code
and be in the loop always, and really understand what's going wrong.
I had architectural opinions about how I wanted it to work.
I didn't want the thing to collapse into chaos as it got larger.
I mean, I've talked a lot of people who said, yeah, after 100,000 lines of code,
the AI can't do anything anymore.
It's terrible.
Give up.
I've worked in security a lot and performance
engineering and things like that.
And so I've got opinions about security.
Good.
And I was trying to not automate everything up front
because I want to know what went wrong.
So doing a real human in the loop thing and and the other kind of question
I want to answer for myself was like, what can we achieve without coding?
Can we be really ambitious and build things we never would have tried to build?
You know?
I know people who build database startups, and it takes a decade and it's kind of
a hard slog.
It's like, if we can do this in less time,
we can build more of these interesting systems.
I like building and using.
So that was what I tried to find out. And.
I like this quote from Deming Deming's right about quality.
And in he introduced quality control to Japan
after the war, you know, inspection of quality.
I know looking at the lines of code does not actually find the bugs.
We know that.
And so you have to build quality in as you go along.
And one of the important things to do that with obviously is testing.
You know.
And so I was like, well, I'm going to build lots and lots of tests and
just using testing, I think,
you know, works really well on small projects.
When you're doing a small AI project, you can really, really test it extensively.
You can be
kind of ruthless about it, and you can be pretty happy
that it's actually working for you and that, you know, it's simple.
But once you get into these larger projects, testing gets more complicated.
I found, you know, especially when you get into
systems, you get into race conditions and you get into weird things.
We talk about in a minute.
And I keep hearing people say,
well, with AI, all you need is 100% statement coverage and you're done.
And it's like,
so but I did try that.
I started off trying to get 100% test coverage.
It seemed like a good idea.
And I also measured different measures of hundred of test coverage
from test coverage, from integration tests.
And it didn't
really didn't really help a lot.
I found they were kind of better uses of my time than trying to get 100%.
You know, I sat down and I asked AI agent to get 100% test coverage.
It kind of wrote trivial tests that were like,
I don't, you know, this is a stupid test.
I don't care about that.
And there's also a
lot of weird error cases that are really hard to cover.
I mean, I went through and asked the agent,
like, well, why haven't we got 100% coverage from this?
It was like,
we don't have a test for when the random number generator in the system fails.
And I was like, yeah, I don't think I want to write a test for that.
Like, let's just to too much error injection.
Like I can see that there's a, you know, it's going to it's going
to give an error or it's going to panic and that's the right behavior.
I don't need to have test coverage for that on all my test suite.
But I still have a lot of tests.
I mean, 75% of my code base tests, test
coverage is between 75 and 100% for each file.
Like, it's like you can still have a lot of tests
without being really obsessive, about 100% test coverage,
which I think is not really the right kind of aim.
The great thing about
copying an existing system like S3 is you've got this test oracle.
You can find out what happens when you do something.
You run the test, you can run it against the you can run it in my case against S3,
and I have 1500 tests that run against S3 and they lock down the behavior.
Then you tell the AI you have to do it exactly like that,
and it's much better at doing things when it does that,
you know, it basically gives it a nice baseline.
It's so much so that I actually think that if you're writing a complex system,
the one way to start is to write
a really, really simple version that's kind of trivial,
that basically has the same behavior that you can use as this test oracle, so
that when you're building a more complex version, you don't make it break.
And you can build a test suite against a simple version first.
It's not 100%
easy like you pointed at Amazon S3, for example, and you discover
all sorts of kind of weird things like S3.
Authorization is a lot of it's eventually consistent, not immediate.
So you have to keep working out well.
We need a load of retries in this test.
Otherwise it'll it looks like it's a the behavior
is different and things like that.
And so you have to kind of do some interpretation
even with a kind of exact text oracle which is kind of annoying.
So it's not it's not quite a specification,
but it kind of does keep you very, very grounded, which is really important.
The other thing about having a test oracle of something you're trying to copy,
whether it's an existing system of yours or someone else's, is that
the public API doesn't cover behavior
you can't really see that goes on in the background.
And so you can't tell
when things happen or invisible behaviors about things.
You have to kind of either infer them from something you can observe, or
you need to find some other way of testing those kind of behaviors.
So you can't see
when an item really gets deleted in S3.
It kind of happens at some point.
But you know, you there's no API that lets
you see behind the scenes of that.
The other thing,
like you think S3 is really nicely documented.
It's got all these hundreds of pages of documentation.
The documentation turns out to mostly be wrong.
And every single detail when you actually look at the details.
So again, having the test oracle and running
the test is much more important than reading the documentation.
If you I think the documentation, you know,
maybe it was true once, maybe it was, maybe it's approximately true.
It kind of gives you hints about things that are interesting, but
never trust anyone's documentation at all.
But again, that gives you grounded tests
on what real behavior is and real edge cases.
Edge cases are really interesting
because they kind of it was it was kind of a while.
And when I found when I was actually working on
improving the type system in the code, and the AI was writing
some test cases for this random against S3 and found a 500 error,
which was repeatable.
And that was kind of quite exciting because this was,
you know, this was an interesting edge case that had come up.
It was implementing the code, and it just thought, well,
I'll test this against S3 and see what happens.
And clearly Amazon did not have a test case for this.
And I did.
And it actually gave me confidence that I was fine as soon as I found that
I was like my test suites actually good now or parts of it are good now
because I'm finding really weird errors and really weird edge cases.
That means I must have kind of explored a lot of the of the universe of testing.
And so it's kind of because it's kind of weird when you're doing this
kind of complex development, because sometimes you feel everything's
terrible and everything is really bad, and like, this is never going to work.
And then other times you feel, oh, actually, yeah,
this is kind of working again.
So this was kind of
the kind of thing about testing that gives you this kind of confidence.
It found another one, another repeatable 500 error later
in another weird edge case.
And I was like, okay, how many of these there are any two so far?
It was.
So I was quite good at the edge cases,
particularly kind of when it's actually writing, writing code itself.
It was.
I kept finding edge cases by reading the
AWS documentation thinking.
Is that really true?
Have we got tests for this?
Asking the AI to write tests for them, and finding other weird things that were
approximately equal to the documentation or hints from the documentation.
When I pointed the AI at the docs
and asked it to do the same thing, it was really bad at that.
It seemed to not be able to look at docs and find edge cases
in the way that I can, so that was kind of interesting.
But so but sometimes if you asked it,
if I mean, sometimes I found edge cases through test coverage issues
like we haven't make sure we've got improving test coverage.
We'll find some edge cases.
Just asking you to think about the usual kind of edge cases, like zero
length and one length and 10,001 length and so on helped a bit.
But, you know, you kind of have to iterate
through these things and kind of think about, think, think like,
think like a shape and think, think like a tester yourself and
have some ideas about areas
that might have weird errors.
Flaky tests were really interesting.
I said that like AWS was AWS converges to truth over time,
which is really annoying and this wasted a huge amount of time.
I like
never have flaky tests with AI is my hard rule.
Just fix them immediately.
It's weird things go wrong sometimes.
It decides that the training data says that developers never fix flaky tests,
so we ignore them.
And I then shout at it and say no.
In this code base, we fix our flaky tests.
It says so in the agents.md file, and you're ignoring it again.
But somehow the training data says no one fixes flaky test,
which was definitely true.
I've worked in many places that had a lot of flaky tests.
Sometimes with the AWS tests, it decides
that I do changes their behavior every day.
We'll just change the code to match again because we must match AWS behavior.
So we and then it's like, oh no, it's changed back again.
Okay, well we'll change that again.
And it's like, no, there's something wrong with the test.
You've got to fix the test first.
So that was kind of annoying.
So I, I would absolutely like
like this is the opportunity to fix flaky tests.
AI is good at it
and it will and it will really help your tests.
If you just get rid of all your flaky tests and also make your test
as fast as possible and run them a lot, you'll then find the flakes much quicker
because most flakes don't happen that often.
I currently have 5000 tests that run in two minutes,
and that's kind of two minutes.
Is my kind of borderline acceptable.
I might try and speed them up again,
but it's like, you know, that's to me, that's okay.
But they have to, you know, you're running them a lot
and say, and you need to find the flakes.
And sometimes with certain kinds of change, you get a lot of flakiness.
And, and then I've spent like, you know, I've set off overnight
runs, doing repeated
test runs to try and find errors on multiple machines and things like that.
So, you know, it's it's not nice if it's slow or,
or the tests really are flaky for some reason.
AI's great at all sorts of kinds of tests.
I basically every now and again I would ask it things like what?
What kind of tests should we have had to fix those issues
we just had, and it would come up with new kinds of tests.
And many of them found issues.
The fuzz tests were good.
The property based testing found some issues, like.
So I think you can
you can do things that you might not have ever thought about before.
There's lots of great kinds of testing
that are available and you should try.
You should try them and see how they work and have more tests, more
kinds of tests as well.
What Jess can't find
is important to know and understand.
Sometimes they can find race conditions
and again, like the more tests you have and the more faster they are, the better.
But it's it's hard performance tests.
We'll talk about it again in a minute.
It's it's
hard to have good performance tests on an ongoing basis.
But you can do it.
You can't find security issues with tests.
You can't decide if your architecture is good with tests
and if you can't measure it right now, you can't really test it or, you know,
so there's lots of things that you have to kind of think
are outside your test and try and work out how to get them inside.
And that's, that's,
you know,
you've got to you've got to be thinking about
these issues that your tests are not finding.
And again, that's why just focusing on test coverage
means you're not thinking about security enough.
To make things more testable.
You know, you've got to think about things
that any kind of signal you can get out of the black box.
Basically, if there's a meow noise, then
it's giving you information that you need to know.
Increase
the scope of what you can test like build more testable interfaces.
One thing I kind of regret doing is not really building the management
and reporting and back end interfaces, because I could have run the tests
on on those to understand what's going on better.
I was really focusing on the public API because that's the thing I felt
I was trying to replicate and not the internals.
I have unit tests on them, but it's the API is a kind of internal
and unstructured, and I don't necessarily know
how much I trust them because I can't see them.
I can only see them through the testing and I can't sit there and play with them.
So I kind of like the more you build out, the better.
Tracing and
and classic observability pieces.
I discovered that like even just getting the AI to build a
hand-built, hand maintained tracing framework was incredibly useful.
You don't need to tie it into production system or something,
but anything that can give it traces that it can look at to debug
is amazingly useful.
It in this case it had a bunch of overheads,
so when I used it for performance testing it was a little bit misleading.
But it told it, you know, basically gave where the the big
the big performance gaps were.
And it was incredibly useful for debugging because I could give it,
you know, I could run the test,
I could have my test suites running, looking for race conditions or errors,
give it a trace and say this happened overnight in my overnight run.
We need to fix this.
And it would
it would let it actually lock down on
what the real problem was rather than trying to guess.
Because if you if you give an AI a bug
but you don't know how to repro it, and it's a very it's a rare condition.
It can waste a lot of time either.
I mean, it can either fail to reproduce itself or it can guess what
the solution might be and get it wrong or something.
And if you can give it a trace and some trace tooling
and just get it to sit there and try and reproduce it
and itself and see if it's the same thing, then it usually can.
And that works really well.
So you don't need to necessarily hook it up to a production environment.
You can really do this just by building, by getting the
AI to build some tracing tools for you.
Performance testing I found the AI is very much like human people
doing performance tests, performance improvements like you build something,
it wouldn't improve the performance or it would make it worse
because it would think this must be the way to fix this.
And it's not.
And that's just the way of performance engineering,
to be honest, and kind of lean into that.
Just remember, this is cheap, low cost work and you just throw it away.
If it doesn't work, don't do it just because it seemed a good idea and keep it.
It's like generally just just say no, throw that one away and try
something else.
Comparing performance against other systems was quite fun.
I, I did some performance testing against one of the other S3 implementations
and got the read performance to be the same, and that was nice.
And then I was like, why is our right performance really slow?
And it spent a bunch of time
thinking and said eventually it said they've got a comment in the code
saying we haven't done.
We don't f sync when we actually write.
And okay, well,
if you don't have synchrony right, then of course it's going to be faster.
Stop wasting my time trying to actually make performance
the same as something that's doing something we don't want to do. So.
But
it's a good it's good tool for that.
Other things I had a lot of issues early
on with with how permission checking worked and time of check
time of use testing permissions twice in different places.
I tried tracing these and fixing some issues, but ended up
just telling it to fix it in the type system instead of actually
trying to use tracing or anything to do this, like have an authorized request type
that can't be authorized, make make sure that all the things going into,
you know, at this gate or all authorized, all these types of functions
take authorized requests and then just force force everything through types.
And that saves a lot of effort.
And, you know, once you've once you've constructed it so you can't
you don't have to have a test for this anymore
because you know that the the types are enforcing it for you.
And I spent a lot of time like looking at the interface types
between modules and just seeing if they looked sane.
Security reviews are used.
I like Codex Security.
I found a lot of issues.
I what I do with them is I
check the findings into the repo and ask the AI to review them.
Three quarters of them are valid.
They're not necessarily 100% security findings.
And then I would every now and again, I'd do review sessions for like,
how could we have avoided these?
What tests should we have that would fix these?
I found it a really valuable because although I do a lot of AI code review
at the time and find a lot of issues and do a lot of review iteration,
it still found things that had been missed that were actually important
and really quite
kind of kind of major things.
So I.
I and so I've done
more kinds of AI security review as well.
I mean Codex security reviews, pull requests, which is fine.
But you also want to sit down and just review the state of the code
as it is as a whole and look for issues and so on.
I found that I found there's been very valuable,
as I said, human in the loop.
I view myself as part of the feedback loop.
I have opinions and I'm here to find out what's going wrong.
And and you know,
so I've been
not trying to automate things too much because I want to actually understand
what's going wrong in order that I can because I'm
I'm responsible for the quality, and I care about the code,
and I want to know it's good because that's my kind of aim with this.
So I kind of view myself as part of that.
So what did we learn?
So a test oracle or model is really useful.
And copying things
that exist is actually a nice activity.
That's long history of open source projects doing that.
The new project was there to replicate Unix and so on.
And you know, it's a great activity to do
and it's kind of good fun and it works quite well.
This is my GitHub commit graph.
As you can see.
Refactoring like you have to do a normal amount of refactoring.
The ridiculous week in the middle, where I was
120,000 lines plus and 75,000 lines minus.
Part of that was that was just I basically had these refactoring weeks
where there's another one at the beginning and I would just refactor stuff.
There was one 43,000 line single file that had to be refactored
at that point as well, which is kind of the agents got there.
But like refactoring is part of the feedback loop.
Don't I don't don't feel you have to one shot
things like you're converging on a better answer
and you're a better program and you've got no time to do that.
And you need to sit there and think, well, yeah, we made some progress.
We got some features done.
But you know what could be better still?
And that feedback loop is, you know, it's the kind of outer harness of
your work. And
and you mustn't ignore that.
Tests are really discovery tools.
They're not like it's not that there's an answer.
And if you had the right of tests, it's there.
You kind of you need to expand the tests of your uncertain and
where you think where you're suspicious and you think there might be more errors.
Work out new things you can add tests to,
and just kind of it's part of your kind of quality control.
Thought about what's going on and like, am I, am I happy about this?
Do I think this code is looking good or do I am I worried?
And if it's worried, you probably want to add more tests and,
you know, kind of bear more time trying to trying to break things
because your role is to is to be there and break things and get them fixed.
I'm going to open source code in a week or so, when I've just finished
the distributed systems bits, again, when I'm happy with it.
So if you want to have a look, sign up and I'll send you a mail when it's ready.
And we got a couple of minutes for questions.
Thank you.
Justin, any questions in the room,
please put your hands up and I'll run over to you
with the mic or there's a gentleman there as well.
Any questions?
One in the middle of the.
With the tables is a little bit trickier,
Did you
did you experiment with any formal verification
or testing tools for the distributed system part?
Not yet. Because I'm quite.
I'm still working through it.
I'm I want to next I'm
looking at basically I mean I.
Yeah, I'm
basically to look at verification tools as soon as it's kind of fully implemented.
I'm like,
I have a sort of huge transition plan from the single host of the multi host.
And like all the bits of it being worked through and I'm hoping like next week
it'll be runnable as fully distributed and
and so yeah, yeah I'm
yeah I'm really interested in what I can do there
because I think there's probably going to be some bugs and I'm
you know, I've been I've been looking at those tools for quite a while.
And I'm really interested in that space
and what you can, what you can verify and what you can formally verify.
I'm formal verification is like something that I'd love to do more of.
And it's kind of something that
there's
mixed reports about how good AI is at it as well.
And I'm really fascinated in that area.
So yes.
It's one right at the back, one that.
Hi, thanks for that.
Absolutely brilliant.
Quite.
You know, it's uncanny how similar to what I'm doing.
And I don't know how you will, you know, just think about this question.
But the challenge I had and I think you are bound to have it
with a test Oracle is,
as the AI loves telling you, that.
Oh, that would be a tautology, because when you're building a system
and you have a test oracle, the test oracle has to work on
an entirely different way of doing the exact same thing with the system
you're testing, so that you're not just running the logic
twice, which would naturally produce the same output.
So the big difficulty
I had was implementing the system using the AI,
and then implementing the test oracle
to follow an entirely different way of achieving the same outcome,
so that, you know, these two keep each other in check.
So this may be a, you know, just maybe
we're doing entirely different things, but does that sound familiar?
Did you think or did you have to fight that?
Yeah.
I mean, I think it was slightly easier because S3 was it was so external and like
just there and like I had some similar issues though with,
with some of the model testing, it set up where it was like,
what am I actually testing?
Anything that's different from the code.
And I think that, yeah.
And I think that I said that I will build an Oracle
even if I was building a complex software, but I think I would probably build it
maybe outside the repo or something as a fixed like, very model of it.
That was.
Yeah.
Because I think you can end up in this situation where you turn out
you're not really testing anything at all.
That's not the same as the thing you're testing.
And you need to you need to have that sort of fixed
guarantee that it's what you want.
And
and yeah, it's definitely easier when you've got an external system
you're copying or something that you can really nail down that.
That's true.
Awesome.
That's all the time we have questions, but please give it up for Justin.